Guide to the Donaldson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donaldson family papers
1870-1971
MS 1699
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.25
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, and photographs documenting the personal and professional lives of the Donaldson family. The papers are arranged in eight series. Each series documents the life of an individual family member and almost all the series contain correspondence, subject files, and photographs.
Donaldson family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased from Charles Apfelbaum in 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in eight series:
I. Harry Nash Donaldson, 1923-1938.
II. Henry Herbert Donaldson, 1910-1938.
III. Hildegarde Nash Donaldson, 1898-1948.
IV. Norman Vaux Donaldson, 1899-1964.
V. Virginia Louise Donaldson, 1919-1960.
VI. Mabel Virginia Nash, 1898-1959.
VII. Mabel W. Nash, 1890-1914.
VIII. General, 1870-1971.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Herbert Donaldson was born in Yonkers, New York, on April 20, 1857. He became an accomplished professor of neurology at various universities and served as president of several professional associations. In 1884 he married Julia Desboro Vaux, who died in 1894. They had two sons, Norman Vaux and John Calvert Donaldson. In 1907 he married Emma Brace. Henry Donaldson died of pneumonia and heart failure on January 23, 1938.
Norman Donaldson graduated from Yale University in 1915 and was a member of the Scroll and Key society. He married Hildegarde Beardsley Nash in 1917. Norman Donaldson worked at the Yale University Press and was appointed director of the Press in 1950. He retired in 1959 and died in 1964.
Hildegarde Nash Donaldson was born in Belgium on June 19, 1893, the daughter of James and Mabel W. Nash. Her father died in 1904; her mother died in 1914, leaving Hildegarde as guardian of her younger sister, Mabel Virginia "Gin" Nash. Mabel Virginia Nash lived in Paris much of her life and did not marry. During World War II she was imprisoned along with other American citizens by German forces occupying France. Mabel Virginia Nash died in Paris in 1957 of complications from alcoholism.
Hildegarde Nash Donaldson was an accomplished violinist, performing her first concert at age eighteen. She graduated in 1912 from the Royal Conservatory of Music in Brussels, where she studied violin under Alfred Marchot. Later she became a pupil of Leopold Auer and also studied with Charles Martin Loeffler in Boston, and toured the United States and Europe. She made a yearly tour of Europe and regularly performed in New England venues until her retirement in 1941. She died of arthritis in Taos, New Mexico in 1946.
Norman and Hildegarde lived in New Haven throughout their marriage. Sailing and fishing in Maine were family pastimes; they also made several trips to Italy. They had two children: Virginia Louise "Midge" Donaldson (born 1918) and Harry Nash "Sonny" Donaldson (born 1920). Midge Donaldson was an actress in theater on and off Broadway who used the stage name Eve Hastings. Sonny Donaldson attended Phillips Academy, Andover, and Rennselaer Polytechnic Institute and worked as an engineer. He married Julie Mildred Felter and they had one child, Carol Lynn Donaldson.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, and photographs documenting the personal and professional lives of the Donaldson family. The papers are arranged in eight series. Each series documents the life of an individual family member and almost all the series contain correspondence, subject files, and photographs.
Genealogy; Publishers and publishing; University presses; Violin -- Performance; Violinists; Donaldson, Hildegarde Nash; Donaldson, Norman Vaux, 1891-1964; Yale University Press
- Harry Nash Donaldson, 1923-1938
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - A-Z [general], 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Donaldson, Norman [father], 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Donaldson, Virginia Louise "Midge" [sister], 1934-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Outgoing, 1932, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files
    - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Education, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    General
    See also: Oversize, folder 1
- Henry Herbert Donaldson, 1910-1938
  General note
  See also:
  - Correspondence
    - Donaldson, John [son], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Donaldson, Norman V. [son], 1910, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Biographies, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Hildegarde Nash Donaldson, 1898-1948
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - A-Z [general], 1915-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Ames, Elizabeth, 1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Baitsell, Dorothy, 1918, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Bellinger, Alfred, 1929-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Bennett, Charles, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Boepple, Gabrielle, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Carrigan, John, 1931-1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Clifton, Susan [grandmother], 1898-1899 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Cook, Judd, 1931- 1934 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Donaldson, Harry [son], 1930-1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Donaldson, Henry [father-in-law], 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Donaldson, Norman [husband], 1923-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Donaldson, Virginia "Midge" [daughter], 1928-1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
      - Follett, Barbara, 1926-1927, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Follett, Helen, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Hibbs, Dave, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Jeffers, Robinson, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Levens, Robert, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Lewis, Penelope, 1928, 1932, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - McAfee, Helen, 1929-1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Moore, Douglas, 1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Morrison, Jimmy, 1929-1938, 1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
      - Mortari, Virgilio, 1928, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Nash, James [father], 1895 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Nash, Mabel Virginia "Gin" [sister], 1918, 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Nash, Mabel W. [mother], undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Nicolet, G.P., 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Phelps, William Lyon, 1931, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Porter, Quincy, 1930, 1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Reynolds, Mynie, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Ross, Louise, 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Simonds, Bruce, 1918-1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Simonds, Rosalind, 1921-1923 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Trueblood, Sarah, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - "Kit", 1932, 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - "Helen and Wilson", 1923 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - "Martin", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Unidentified last name, 1915-1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Outgoing
      - A-Z [general], 1919, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Troy, Hesse, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Subject Files
    - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 43-46)
    - Concert programs, 1911-1940, undated (Box 5, Folder 47-49)
    - Death, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Donaldson, Virginia Louise [birth of daughter], 1918 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Financial, 1920-1948 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - "Genius Burning" [writing journal of Reynolds family], 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Music clubs, 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Passport, 1935, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Photographs
    - "The Cottage," 1923-1926, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Violin, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Wedding, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Portraits, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Norman Vaux Donaldson, 1899-1964
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - A-Z [general], 1927-1964, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Bellinger, Alfred, 1929, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Day, George Parmly, 1944, 1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Donaldson, Emma Brace [mother], undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Donaldson, Harry Nash "Sonny" [son], 1935-1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Donaldson, Henry H. [father], 1925, 1927, 1932, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Donaldson, Hildegarde Nash [wife], 1927-1928, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Donaldson, John Calvert [brother], 1905-1956, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Donaldson, Julia [niece], 1931 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Donaldson, Julie [daughter-in-law], 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Donaldson, Virginia Louise "Midge" [daughter], 1927-1943, undated (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
      - Follett, Barbara Wilson, 1928-1933, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Follett, Helen, 1929, 1947, 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Griswold, A. Whitney, 1950, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Henkel, Frances [Mrs. Paul Henkel], 1934, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Hutchins, Robert, 1939, 1942, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Levens family, 1938-1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Lewis, Penelope, 1934-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Morrison, Jimmy, 1931-1932, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Nash, Mabel Virginia "Gin" [sister-in-law], 1929-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Podoloff, Jacob [United States Department of State], 1948 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Porter, Quincy, 1934, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Pound, Ezra, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Reynolds, Diana, 1926-1931, 1933, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - Reynolds, Mynie, 1927-1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Reynolds, Pamela, 1926-1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - Reynolds, Richard, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Russell, Thomas, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Simonds, Bruce, 1918-1923 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Trafford, Sarah, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Troy, Hesse, 1958-1959, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Vaux, Mrs. C. Boyer, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 34)
      - Williams, Stanley, 1950, undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
      - Zilboorg, Gregory [Hildegarde Donaldson's doctor], 1946 (Box 7, Folder 36)
      - "Katherine," 1947-1948, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
      - "Louise," 1938, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
      - Unidentified, 1923-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Outgoing
      - A-Z [general], 1899-1959, undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
      - Donaldson, Emma Brace [stepmother], 1915-1917 (Box 7, Folder 41)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1938 (Box 7, Folder 42)
      - "Auntie Emma", 1907 (Box 7, Folder 43)
      - "Uncle Bow", 1917 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Subject Files
    - Capri, Italy [trip], 1926 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Christmas cards, 1927, 1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Clubs, 1911-1952, undated (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Diary, 1923-1925, undated (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Financial, 1920-1957, undated (Box 8, Folder 50-52)
    - Lists [includes personal calendar], 1940-1961, undated (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Medical diary, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Personal notebooks [diary, Christmas gift list, Plato's Republic, etc.], 1907-1920, 1926, undated (Box 8, Folder 55-56)
    - Sailing, 1936, undated (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Sympathy correspondence
      - Donaldson, Henry H. [death], 1938 (Box 9, Folder 58)
      - Donaldson, Hildegarde N. [death], 1946 (Box 9, Folder 59-61)
    - Writings [includes poetry], 1915, 1925, undated (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Yale University Faculty Committee For Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children, 1940-1944, undated (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Yale University Press
      - General, 1935-1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 64)
      - Appointment as director, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 65)
      - Lewis, W. P., 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 66)
      - Misappropriation of funds, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 67)
      - Pamphlets and articles, 1914, 1919, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Photographs
    - General, undated (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - Yale University Press, undated (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - Youth, 1914, undated (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - Photo albums, 1906-1923, 1944, undated (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Portraits, undated (Box 10, Folder 73)
- Virginia Louise Donaldson, 1919-1960
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - A-Z [general], 1935-1945, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Donaldson, Harry N. "Sonny" [brother], 1938, 1943, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Donaldson, Henry H. [grandfather], 1937 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Donaldson, Hildegarde [mother], 1929-1941, undated (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
      - Donaldson, Norman V. [father], 1935-1945, undated (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
      - Lewis, Penelope, 1919, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Morrison, Jimmy, 1937, 1946, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Nash, Mabel Virginia "Gin" [aunt], undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Trueblood, Sarah S. "Sal" [sister of Dr. Benjamin Spock '24], 1937-1944, undated (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
      - "Boris", 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - "Eric" [a.k.a. "Fritz"], 1942-1945 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - "Ruthie", 1932, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - "Stan", undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - "Vera", undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - "Wal", 1944-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Outgoing
      - A-Z [general], 1923-1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - Coolidge, Calvin, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - Trueblood, Sarah S. "Sal" [sister of Dr. Benjamin Spock '24], 1939-1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - "Beantuffit", undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - "Grandma", 1932, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Subject Files
    - Donaldson, Hildegarde N. [letters of condolence on her death], 1946 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Education, 1932, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Finances, 1949-1960, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Hair [sixteen months old], 1919 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Theater, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Photographs
    - Theater, undated (Box 12, Folder 29-30)
    - Photo albums, 1928-1933, undated (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Portraits, 1932, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 32)
- Mabel Virginia Nash, 1898-1959
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z [general], 1914, 1927, 1936, 1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Clifton, Susan [grandmother], 1898-1899, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Donaldson, Hildegarde [sister], undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Subject Files
    - Death
      - General, 1938, 1956-1959, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Bankers Trust Company, 1954-1959, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Marshall, Mrs. George C., 1957 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Pellerin Company, 1929, 1938, 1957-1959, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Stepan, Arpinee, 1956-1958, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Wiart, Anne, 1957, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Wiggin Dana, 1957-1959 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Finances, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Prisoner of war, 1940-1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Mabel W. Nash, 1890-1914
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1891, 1908, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Joan, Will, 1890-1891, 1893, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Otis, Raymond, 1890 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Subject Files
    - Sympathy correspondence [death of James Nash, husband], 1904 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Travel, 1906, 1914 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- General, 1870-1971
  - Correspondence
    - Family [letter from E. Root to Alfred Donaldson and from "Julia" to "mother"], 1870, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified, 1918-1947, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Subject Files
    - Churches, 1929, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Poetry, 1922-1942, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - War diaries [written by "J.W.C." re: experiences in WWII], 1942-1944, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Wills, 1918-1953 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Writing, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - "Alice W. And Wedding" [contains negatives only], undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Donaldson, Harry Nash and Virginia Louise, 1921, 1928, 1933-1935, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Europe, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - 14 Briar Lane, New Haven, Connecticut [home], undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Great Chebeague, Maine, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Homes, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Sailing [mostly unidentified], 1914, 1924-1925, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - "Scanticut" [contains negatives only], undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - United States [travel to: Mohawk Park, Mt. Vernon, Arizona, New Hampshire], 1926, 1938, 1940, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Washington, D.C., undated (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Yellowstone, undated (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified [contains some negatives], 1906, 1923-1924, 1939-1940, 1948, 1971, undated (Box 17, Folder 19-24)
- Oversize, 1870-1971
  - Photographs (Box 18, Folder 1)